so hi everyone welcome to uh this week's magnet
seminar it's good to see uh another good uh
turnout today for those who who are new to our
seminar series um we will have a sort of 20 to
30 minute presentation and we kindly ask that you
keep your microphones muted so as not to interrupt
the speaker if you are having problems with your
video connection and your internet connection
turning off your video um can
actually help and improve that
at the end of the session um we'll have time for
for a 10 to 15 minute question and discussion
section um we'll ask you to raise your hands via
zoom if you don't want to ask your question in
person by all means please just type it into the
chat and myself or one of the other co-hosts will
read it out for you and at the end of of
our seminar we'll have time for an informal
catch-up a bit of a social um aspect of people are
interested in hanging around for a chat and this
part of the seminar series isn't recorded um so it
won't appear um in in the public youtube channel
so today i'm pleased to say that we have sanjay
panoska from gfc potsdam in germany and she will
be talking about some long-term global models of
geomagnetic field behavior so i will pass over
to you sanja thank you thanks a lot
so i start sharing the screen now
um well it's my pleasure today
to present our recent work on
long-term global geomagnetic field models with
special attention on geomagnetic excursions
limitation on the models attempts to try to
overcome some limitations and applications
and actually one application production
of cosmogenic size to production rates
so it's a list of collaborators here more
or less in the order the study appears
and because i will speak about excursions a lot um
almost on every slide in this presentation what a
better way to to explain what these events
are for those of you who haven't worked on
and here's magnetic field lines from the um
historical film model but the float looks
very similar today so it's double dominated
this is epoch 1980 and then on the other hand
on the right right hand side we have the la
champ exclusion that happened 41 000 years ago
and it's the best documented excursion and the
most recent global event and we see later by
and uh how many there are more um and this the
sharp exclusion is from from a model that i will
present in uh shortly uh so we know that magnetic
field is constantly changing in time and space
and the two most extreme variations of reversal
and excursions for the reversal and excursions the
field um dramatically decreasing intensity
and also exhibits uh multipolar behavior
as presented here for the for the lachang
exclusion um the motivation for the study
uh from from direct observations and here i put
the igrf model in figure a uh we know that the
axial dipole is decreasing the intensity of
the field is decreasing that's for the past
100 years and we can uh use here one forecast
of the model and see that the field will
uh continue to decrease or to decay for for
the next uh 100 years so it's a question uh
that's the open question will the
field go to a reversal or excursion
and we will have a look uh on this
question from from palu magnetic models
um and for for building these models we use uh
parliamentary records from sediments and uh rocks
lava flows um and this is one example the record
from black sea measures here and uh gfc and one
of the best records we have on this time scale uh
this is zero to seven seventy hundred years ago
so we have the three components declination
inclination and intensity and the red lines
are the la champ event that i mentioned uh
and and what you see on this time series that
for this event for this exclusion we have a large
deviation in directions in both declination and
inclination and a low field intensity uh then we
can having having global models we can have a look
how low was the field globally and this is here
one example we'll have more and time dependence
later few snapshots of the field um but for
a start uh this is for an older model 100k
ggf100k and we compare this field
intensity at the earth's surface
with the present day field on the same color scale
um the black line is the south atlantic anomaly
so the region with the lowest flowing density we
have today and over the last jump more or less the
the maximum field intensity it's lower than the
one we have today over the south london anomaly
so it gets really low globally um just a short
overview of what exists on this long time scales
and this figure i've made and included models that
cover the holocene which are not here because the
picture gets really long so there are a couple of
models that exist on closing time scale on very
long time scales we know about the time average
fields for million year five or 10 million years
for the period in between we have two kind kind of
models of reconstructions one are global spherical
harmonics colored in green here and the others
are stacks or relative value intensity stacks or
uh actual dipole moment variation curves
uh in in blue dark blue for the global or
um light blue for the original and when we have
intensity records from from from a given region
so for the for the global models for the green
one we have a few um actually two and and three
actually now for the fred de la shum event uh
one model for the for the iceland basin excursion
two for the matoyama brune and the longest
reconstruction that we have so far it's uh that
goes beyond the whole scene is the gg500k model
um but today i'll present uh and the newest model
the 70k which we tried to get a a better
resolution compared to our previous reconstruction
um and that's the only sliding that i have
from the from the 100k model just to say we can
reconstruct the field in time and space globally
a few snapshots compared to the present day field
and i have to say in this in this model
this model is built with um it's based on a
considerable amount of data over 100 records
um and we really didn't have we had really
loose criteria so the the in this criteria in
in selecting the records only records that were
independently dated so it means that records dated
with uh rpi or polio second variation correlation
were not included in the model and we have some
records with the low resolution we try to overcome
this with some smoothing kernels uh also some
inconsistent age so in general the mode the model
is uh rather smooth um and we learn from this
model and we to the other end we say let's use um
a really strict selection criteria listed here
globally distributed size high resolution data
meaning meaning high sedimentation rates three
components and validated um and updated phonology
so here is the list of the records we used
and this this is a challenging task so for the
for the data available we selected nine records
um the red means that the rent in the in the list
denotes the when we updated the h model on the
map and on a we have the location on these records
and the color map is the sensitivity kernels
which means and these maps is so it's an average
over the past seventy thousand years and um
also also that gives an indication about the
number of data in this in these records in
in general um no no records no location no
no region is unrepresented but um we see
some some um low low sensitivity regions
for the temporal resolution so it's important
distribution uh we have the the plot on b and
the temporal distribution of data does not uh
vary much so we have more or less all the periods
covered by data the number of data goes a little
bit lower towards the both ends of the model
and it covers the period 15 to 70 so it does not
include the holocene a few details about the model
not giving equations uh i mentioned the selection
criteria then the pilot intensity records will
were calibrated prior to inversion this is in
contrast with the 100k model when we included
the absolute data from geometry and pin into
the model and calibrated the records within the
inversion here um argo and volcanic data were
not used in the model except for indirectly uh
calibrating the records uh declination are related
to zero main excluding the transitional periods um
for the uncertainty estimates so equally weighted
all records with five micro tesla for intensities
and alpha 95 of 8.5 degrees for directions and
these are converted to standard deviations um
so the spherical harmonic basis function for the
spatial representation uh cubic b splines with no
spacing for 50 years for the temporal dependence
uh starting model starting the inversion from the
axial dipole we use iterative outer rejection
of 5 standard deviations but the amount of data
that we rejected in the final model is really
low and the normalized misfit is about one
um so let's analyze some characteristics of the
model uh on the first uh in a we have the dipole
coefficients variation in time g10 g11 and h11
um the the gray bars are the three exclusions we
have in this period of the norwegian greenland
sea at about 65 000 years ago the champion 41
and monolith auckland did about 34 000 years ago
so what what we see from that the first three
coefficients from the dipole coefficients is that
the axial dipole sig significantly vary in time
but the other two the equatorial dipoles
g1 and h1 one day they vary or oscillate
more or less on the same on the same level in
transitional times and in non-traditional times
the axial dipole is reflected into that type of
moment variations and we uh we see that the diaper
moment uh it's lower over over the la champ it's
about i think five percent of the presentation
i think or it's five was from another model
so one point five percent from this model
um from the norwegian village we have about 20
percent of the present day filled and for the mono
lake about uh 40 percent of the present many field
uh for the dipole latitude we see variations or
deviations for all the excursions were small
for the mono lake and for the norwegian village
about 60 degrees and for the la champ uh it goes
to the opposite hemisphere to minus minus 50
degrees and and the last one is the average psv
index over this time period and the threshold will
be suggested for distinguishing transitional and
non-traditional states of 0.5 um and this combines
the the dipole moment variations in the the pole
position so um any time the field is low and we
have large deviation the index goes up for the
exclusions is obviously uh this is the average
of global average it's above the threshold uh
for the norwegian government as well here we have
a second kind of uh increase uh again we interpret
this as a part of the norwegian premier c
and then uh for the mono lake um that does not
reach the threshold though i have to say i i'm
not presenting here the uh the psv index as
the map but um for the for the monolith we have
some regions when the index increase above the
above the threshold but the mean value is below
um and now let's look at the morphology of the
field um on the left hand side is the total field
intensity at the earth's surface for the three
inverse the virgin greenland still lash champ and
monolake and this is a period of 2000 years about
around this event and the time step is 250 years
uh the all plots are plotted on the same color
scale and here it's a comparison with the igrf
2020 um it's located that into degree
six for super comparison purposes
and on the right hand side is the again the same
event and the same periods and time steps for the
radial component of the field at the cmb
so looking at the the filtering density first
at the earth surface it's really noticeable
that for the lachamp event the field gets really
low for extended periods of time and globally low
um whereas for the norwegian relevancy uh it gets
lower but the the minimum field intensity stays
in the equatorial region or the mid latitudinal
regions for the monolith excursion the field is
decreasing but still uh i think we can see that
we have some dipole star structures still observe
observable for the for this period um for the for
the br for the radial component oops no um for the
for the radial component the at the cmb um
think of it as a as a flux so the blue is
inward the red is outward and when you see red in
the northern hemisphere means reverse flux patches
and blue on the on the southern
hemisphere against moon servers
and and appearance of these reverse flux patches
will decrease the dipole moment of field intensity
um so what what is similar for the for the three
events is for when the fields start to decrease
um this uh reverse flux patches appear in the
equatorial region and and move towards the poles
here for example towards the the northern hemis
northern poles and and the southwest for for this
reverse flux patches for all
events and um for the la champ the
it's a very really complex morphology reverse and
normal fox patches everywhere um and another um
the difference between the la champ and the
new video and monolithic excursion is that
um the reverse flux patches for the shamp event
uh they move toward the poles and they enter the
tangential cylinder uh in both hemisphere and stay
there for an extended period of time which is not
the case for the other two so maybe this is one
hint if excursions are regional or global events
and um because we have a global models we can
have a look at the regional differences um and
here's in terms of time series or predictions so i
i took the locations when we have records and and
um estimated predictions and plot them here as the
virtual type environment ugp latitude and the psv
index so um and i forgot to mention that from
this model from the ggf 70 at the actual dipole
term actually reverses for a short period of time
of 300 years um and this is um as a result of the
intensity records that build the model and they
have this uh dipole low so at the meat of the le
champ excursions you have a low then the field
uh increases intensity and then decreases again
so this increase in intensity the main
point it's reflected in the g10 term
um growing in the opposite direction so
the gray by here is this this time period
um what is um interesting is that uh for all
of this location which are globally distributed
when the field starts to to decrease uh it's
decreasing at the same time or simultaneously
for all locations but then the behavior after
how it develops really varies from location
to location and that's the same is true for
the vgp and reflected also in the psv index
and you see in the in the index that sometimes uh
this is the the dashed line is the the threshold
um so sometimes it goes above the threshold so
it means the field is in transitional state at
this location but can go down in a normal kind
of state and then go again in transitional state
um and we use this uh the psv index on the global
scale as a measure to find the duration of this
event and um so every time we use this threshold
so when the ps index go above 0.5 you say this is
the start a starting age and then uh when even
go it finishes and go below 0.5 it's the nh
i have here the start edge and duration which
is the difference between the the start and the
nh and because of this simultaneous behavior
here um the start age that does not vary a lot
of course we see that it doesn't start the
latin doesn't start everywhere at the same
time but pretty close and the the differences
in the end age are reflected in the duration
so from for this model for the la champ
excursions we have a duration of about 500 to 30
3 400 years uh with a mean of a value of about
1800 years um and i have to say the number we get
for different duration of course it depends
how you how you measure it uh how and which
model model you take but i think we're converging
towards the duration of the le champ excursions
because using using different models as well
as uh i did an analysis on the raw data that
build the 100k model the numbers we get are 1600
1300 uh for one value for rpi stock the duration
was estimated to 1500 so we are more or less on
this range for the for the la shmoop excursion
and then let's look at the energy axle dipole
versus non-axle dipole at the cmb at the earth's
surface and here i compared the three events
so the norwegian green and steel shampoo and
monolake uh axle dipole and in dashline the
non-axle dipole so for for all all of the
events at the cmb uh we have this the same energy
or similar energy for the for the three events
except for the lasham and the axial
dipole it decreases extremely here
at the earth surface expectedly the dipole it's
it's larger than the non-dipole except for it for
the lachamp again here for the norwegian greenland
sea we have again a decrease in the induction
dipole energy but this is more like one order of
magnitude and effort for the monolake is even less
and also the monolake uh that the starting so this
is 5 000 years before and after the exclusion the
midpoint of the excursions the monolith is lower
than the two events and this is because of the how
the field recovers after the shump um and i have
a figure here which is from another model called
ls mode 0.2 uh which is shorter so cover the le
champ exclusion the mono legs the period fifty
to thirty thousand years and um these models agree
quite well with this uh with the 70k model and um
what we suggested for for the la shmoop event uh
in this session when you see the uh the level of
the dipole power and the non-dipole power so the
non-dipole power in this mode and also in our mode
um in our model stay on the on the oscillates
on the similar level um so the dipole is this is
all on the cmb it's uh it's higher for the
pre-lachamp state then uh decreases extremely
and when it recovers dipole it it does recover
but not on the state that's in pre-lachamp and
this situation allows for appearing uh regional
or regional confined excursions like the monolith
and you can have like a monolith uh like like a
double event uh a low at 34 or even even after
31 or 28. um and also it may explain some other
exclusions like that appear later like hilly
napalio you see some um different ages for healing
nepali from from 70 000 years to 22 000 years
and as i mentioned this data set the dataset
we have are limited in time and space in in
resolution and instrumentation rate um so
this is one attempt to build out the first
multi-proxy uh global geomagnetic field model
um we know that cosmogenics isotopes that
are produced in the atmosphere depend on the
geomagnetic field and the solar magnetic field
uh after the production they are deposited and
i will speak about this later they are deposited
in ice and sediments measured and depending
on which time scale you look uh they can be
proxy for the solar variability or the geometric
field and on the time scale we are looking here
they are considered to be a
proxy for the geomagnetic field
so i compiled the data set there are more
records than presented here or used in this study
and by coincidence there are nine records the same
number as the paramagnetic one and actually the
first attempt was to improve the 100k model but
because of the really large number of paramagnetic
data it was difficult to us to um to assess the
influence of the brilliant data into palo magnetic
field model so i end up using the the 70k model
ggfss 70 and complement the poly magnetic records
with beryllium 10. um so locations are given
here we have three records from from greenland
farm from antarctica uh and five sediments
i think portuguese margin south atlantic
and the best equatorial pacific number of
records is not really i mean high compared
to the paleo magnetic and we have increased
number of data here over the la shmoop excursion
the first step towards including these
records in geomagnetic field models
is to um to convert the beryllium 10 to to paleo
intensity so uh in the end uh the code does not
distinguish if these are believe 10 or final
magnetic um not going into details so this is how
the dependence look like between beryllium 10 and
and the adm um i have to say the beryllium name
is also normalized so think of it as a as a rpi
also nrm over some some normalizer to to cancel
some environmental climate uh climate effects
that you have in the signal um after we get the
and here is the same record this is a record from
the best equatorial pacific uh how it looked like
as a function of age the the record the raw data
are the the blue and converted to vadm uh is the
red and we also smoothed the record uh so we don't
have some solar somewhat solar influence in it
um and they also they come into uh
relative form and we use the same
and volcanic data from geometry in pin databases
to to calibrate to absolute before enter them
in the model um just to show you that the
two types of records the two type of proxy
show similar signals or similar variation i
created a stack based on the pyromagnetic data
an axial dipole moment stack in in blue for
the pyromagnetic data and beryllium 10 based
the adm stack here and they compare quite well
the beryllium 10 especially for us they have this
high intensity values here and it's reflected in
the dipole moment and some discrepancies but can
also be problem with ages though with the data
set compiled there are more records but we again
try to extract records below 10 records with uh
the robust results in terms of beryllium 10 and h
and then uh i have three models here that i
compared the one based on paramagnetic data
second one ggfs 70 10b um that used the
beryllium 10 the same way as paramagnetic records
and some studies shows that uh beryllium can uh
only reflect the dipole moment variations so this
was a test to see if we can use the beryllium tent
to influence or or to be a function of the dipole
coefficients only so the 10b deep means it's
a beryllium 10 are considered as a function of
the first three gauss coefficients so these are
the the three models i'm comparing here and um
just as an example i give you two locations the
first one is black sea and pyelon magnetic data
and no brilliant in the region and the the second
location is uh greenland ice core and berlin and
the black circles here um what was here the the
three models agree uh well and actually know
no variations uh in the models but in
the region when we have beryllium 10 data
we have some variations and
reflecting the global feature the diaper moment
uh including the beryllium 10 then uh smooth
out a little bit the the shampoo excursion so the
diaper we get a higher diaper moment over the lash
and also there are some differences um i compared
the fit to the data because it's difficult to
judge which which of the two models that that
includes beryllium is better uh and the misfit
to paramagnetic data to believe the data combine
the two uh it's better for the for the ggfs 7010b
uh but i think still uh there is some work
to be done on brilliant10 before judging
and the last point is application and
that's cosmogenic as the production rate
over the past hundred thousand years
um so you see i used beryllium pen
to try to improve the models and here is a
different different on the other side we can
use the paleomagnetic field models the global
reconstruction to predict the production in the
atmosphere and here i have the ls mode on the next
slides i have uh the all models and the results
i'm going to show you are based on beryllium
10. uh i have estimates for for other isotopes 7
carbon 40 and others but the conclusions i've
made are the same for for other assets as well
um so we have the in blue the dipole moment from
our ls mode from 50 to 30 000 years and i selected
uh three epochs so time when the field
is uh larger than the present day field
which is dashed line here igrf um the meat
of the la champ excursion and the monolake
and these are presented here this is a global
average columnar production of beryllium 10
um so for the for the case when we have a very
high field the lashamp event monolake and 2020
and it's um often it's considered that the field
uh because of the dipole dominance you see the
latitudinal uh dependence in the production rate
which is presented here when the you know you
see the production as a function of latitude and
it is i mean it depends on the latitude for the
three cases except for for the lachan when we have
this uh yeah in almost no latitudinal dependence
uh and high production uh globally for for
the for this time period and that's not the
case only for for this time period uh we found
that for a period of about uh 1600 years which
is actually the duration that we estimated for
the la shmoop excursions um this zonal profiles
they they don't show it to the null behavior so
basically we cannot use the assumption about the
um cut off rigidity based on dipole field or axel
dipole fields to be valid for the lashamp event
and um of course i mentioned that the the
production depends on the two factors of
the geomagnetic field and the solar the
helispheric magnetic field expressed here
as a solar modulation um and i i
tested a few cases uh a range of
values for for the solar modulation
from from no solar modulation to to 2000
mega volts and i plotted again the the ls mode
here uh 10b global 10 beryllium global global
production in this period and of course when there
is no um shielding from the solar magnetic field
uh what we see the the production is is highest
um and actually the peak is when there is also
no shooting in the deal almost no shields showing
of the geomagnetic field over the sump exclusions
and when the values of the solar modulation
are uh high then we don't the signal that we
observed or or we get from the from the geometric
field is uh uh suppressed so we cannot do it well
and you probably have seen this figure when uh
the production rate of cosmogenics is expressed
uh as a function of the two and this is usually
uh based on numerical simulation and this is
the the the plot here it's based on the ls mode
so it's a values from from from our models and
it's a summary of the period 50 to 30 000 years of
course we have more points here when the field is
um a bit higher diaper moment but we have some
some when something slow and i used um i used a 2d
um smoothing splines to to get the surface because
these are discrete points from the model but in
general the production rate over the la champ
excursion the min uh lobega slide before here um
the the production rate the mean production rate
from the ls mode over the la champ excursion um
it's uh more than five than the present-day
field also seen here in the in the 3d plot
um and another interesting features uh is
the first uh to see the robust features or to
robust production because now we have a few models
that cover this long time scale so we can look at
the production from all of the models um and then
um what we observe and from the 100k model agree
well with the whole thing here production it's
a bit the production is lower um than than the
other two the the seven the 70k model and ls
mode and that's because the the 100k predicts
a little bit higher uh higher diaper movement
meaning higher shielding towards the cosmic rays
and also it's smoother but the 70k and the ls mod
they prevail over the overlapping period and i've
also estimated the average production hemispheric
productions on northern hemisphere versus south
and atlantic with the pacific uh and because
we we observe this at um hemispheric asymmetry
at least we we have a paper for the whole policy
models when we have a lower field in the southern
hemisphere and higher higher variability and this
is reflected in the production rates and not only
in the halls in time scale as you can see here and
this is an average over the periods uh this model
covers so in the in the present-day filled igrf
in in the calisthenic case on average over ten
thousand years then ls mode uh in the 70k model
so it's approved seventy to fifteen thousand years
ago and um hundred hundred thousand years ago
they all showed this hemispherical symmetry so
um lower production in the northern hemisphere
uh higher production in southern hemisphere and
no differences in the atlantic versus specific
and and because the the estimates
we have are 3d basically 4d because
we have also the time dependence uh we see
the production in the atmospheric column uh
here expressed uh as atmospheric depth or just to
give you an idea about the the altitude so it's um
20 kilometers to to mean sea level basically
um and these are the same um three epochs i've
selected before for the global maps for the main
production um the the cells and these plots are a
little bit denaliated uh but it's clear that the
maximum production uh it's in the polar region
when we have a dipole-dominated field this is
uh and also actually here you can see uh higher
production in the in the south and latitudes in
the southern polar region compared to the northern
them we have some still some dipolar structure
visible and over the monolithic exclusion
and maximum production everywhere
for the for the la shmoop event
and if we consider this 3d estimate and
the positional model which is based on on
atmospheric circulation uh we can deposit this
production this uh beryllium 10 atoms in the
uh on the surface of the earth and compare
this for example as as given here in the um
comparison with the greenland ice cores so um
here that the three models the 100k the 70k and
the ls mode and and it's absolute so it's uh the
position of flux in absolute units um and i
think the um they defeat the data quite well
um and last but not least just to say that uh the
models and the data i've presented and in codes
for estimating um predictions of the models as
well as animation as as given here which i didn't
have time to present are all available online so
you can download and play with it and have a look
um the cutoff rigidity which is the shielding
of the geomagnetic field from the ls mode is
also available and all of the other models
this paper in review are also available
and hopefully soon the production
rates you will find them also there
so a quick summary um we are slowly
moving uh moving towards i think uh
have global models in the longer and longer
time scales beyond the whole scene the one
i presented cover two three excursions and then
we having these models we can first extract uh
robust features of the models of the
geomagnetic field uh and and test this
event either similar or dissimilar so the
the most the best the best exclusion of the
the best global event is the la champ the most
recent um and it's uh we see from from the from
our from our models uh that it's it's a result of
the actual dramatic axle dipole a decrease and uh
flux patch is moving in the in both reverse fast
partition in both hemispheres uh so beryllium 10
they have limited um i would say for the moment
um again because of the data distribution uh uh
limited effect on the panel
magnetic field models or maybe that
as as we saw that they showed they agree with the
palo palo magnetic records and then having the
models we can estimate the production rates and
compare with the actual measurements thanks a lot
thank you very much sonia we can give a
virtual round of applause via the zoom
reactions it was really interesting uh really
interesting presentation thank you very much
and i can open the floor to to uh
questions um so if somebody if you
would like just raise your hand uh by a zoom or
type a question into the chat if anybody has one
uh carrie yeah i've got so many questions i
don't know where to start that was a lovely
lovely uh uh core dump of everything
that you've done sanyo really impressive
um so uh firstly i wanted to uh think about um
when you do the translation of um beryllium 10
to dipole moment um it must i'm just wondering
how one characterizes the uncertainty in that
because it seems to me that there's a big
issue in your modeling about the balancing
of uncertainties and also about balancing the
numbers of data regionally and uh i uh i i i
don't think we really have a formal way of doing
that is that correct and that's correct um for the
for the model i've presented uh beryllium 10 uh
we debate them the same as the parallel magnetic
record just we didn't want to put more weight on
the on the paramagnetic magnetic or beryllium pen
i remember that some of the beryllium records
unlike the uh the palm intensities or paramagnetic
date in general uh they do come with uncertainty
estimates actually and for the first preliminary
study i did on the 100k model the william 10
records i'm i weighed them according to the
uncertainty estimates so if i have beryllium 10
feet with uh uh yeah uncertainty i convert this to
uh to palo intensity with uncertainties and maybe
that's that i should do now so for the moment
the model i presented it's um it's uh they're all
equilibated so five five micro tesla for intensity
pano magnetic and beryllium ten uh for the
estimating uh uncertainty estimates on the
model uh i haven't done this i'm doing it in
the moment for the 100k model and for the 70k
so i think um we should discuss to put them this
probably also update the files in order to be
described estimates and i'm using the approach
you have used before for the holocene models and
yeah not to hold the floor but uh that it's very
noticeable that there really aren't any records
in the pacific is there any hope for stuff there
yes um oh yes but yes there is it's noticeable
i i know i mean and some some we
have at least from the palo magnetic
site it's a low resolution so yeah
thank you very much kathy um
we'll hand over to to richard now
lovely talk um so my usual standard
question is you discard lots of data
and i fully get that that you want to use high
quality data but out of the data you discarded
how do they look compared with the model something
compare well other others not um it's a i mean
for the 100k model when i when i include them
so it's a large amount of data that yes i agree
some agree well other others not so it seems
like um and that approach was used in ls mode
i think one one have to uh to use maybe first to
check or even create original stacks if you wish
kind of so that the the request is consistent
regionally so but i found and i think that's
why i'm speaking about this loose criteria
we uh we didn't select the data and then uh
if if a record is with higher resolution
your feed is better than the others
uh i checked the 70k model yes it's
a really limited data distribution
uh but i think for the period when that overlaps
with the ls mode we have the similar variation
right because uh yeah monica and i have
had discussions on this and she knows i'm
far more open to grocery data and just letting
the model model have a look at it and see what
it comes up with in particular if you've got
anything in the pacific but um the the old uh the
quote that inadequate data are far better than no
data at all so um i mean you can jiggle with the
um the uncertainties but it would be nice to kind
of squeeze more data and see at what point the
model starts going mad because there's nothing
else people have put a lot of work in collecting
these data i've never done any of the work
but it would i have sympathy for them when
they get completely discarded i
agree and i have to be honest that uh
and that happened with doing modeling that some
good records came out after we did the model
or even before publishing but
the records are constantly coming
so i think it it there there is a potential
for for improving it for adding more records
more good records let's say i would take um
less good records with higher putting in higher
variances and see what happens that's that's just
me and i don't i don't have to do the work so well
as i said this man many times uh i think these
two models uh 70k in the 100k i was really going
to extremes everything nine records probably the
true maybe in between as you said to include more
yeah thank you thank you very much richard um
are there any other questions for for sonya
so if nobody's going to put their hand up i mean
i have a question um when you're looking at the
the change in the power across the the different
excursions the shot really jumps out as being
a a very large drop in the power i mean i'm
wondering how much of that is in relation
to the other excursions i'm wondering how
much of that is is related to difference in
the dynamics of these excursions and how much
might actually be related to biases in the data
the shop is is pretty well studied compared to
the other excursions is it just that we have
more data that are picking out um you know the
resolution of the excursion better or is it that
you know maybe there are some differences in the
dynamics um this is the data i mean if there are
nine records this land records covered
la shmoop and monolith and individual vlc
and just by looking at the raw data not not
the model you see that the intensity also the
direction directional variations are large in
the sum compared to the other so of course the
model has uncertainties the data as well uh but i
don't think it's related to the data at least like
having um uh point five percent of the present-day
model over the la shmoop forty percent of the
monolith or twenty percent over over the norwegian
village here i i don't think the uncertainties
is that big i mean i may prove wrong but i think
these are this distinct event in terms of dynamics
uh and then i think it's a it's just that
some some events are regional some are global
and of course when i say okay we have this
behavior now from the from the lachamp and the
the two other regional events we need more
excursions to really be sure about claims uh
what what drives is it really only
the axial diplo term that changes over
exclusion so i think there's more work to do on
these longer excursions and compared to delashan
thank you very much um we have time for
another question if anybody wants
to to to throw one sign this week
we've got a comment um from nick gargabo in the
chat this is a nice talk um do you have some ideas
on how to measure the quality of data records
so that they can be weighted uh in the averages
uh very good question i um so these records
we speak about sediments now because they are
magnetic and volcanic they cut it they come with
some kind of a measure let's say alpha 95 or we
can we can uh assist uncertainty somehow for the
for the sediments as we don't have uh i think the
the way to go will be of course for the moment i
i put i made everything equally uh i did a study
when i tried to uh that's sort of the whole time
scale actually also on 100k records uh to fit
spline uh just to judge or to assess the random
variability in the records and and um and get
out a random uncertainty estimates compared with
our hero and volcanic to to see if there is some
systematic bias so that that's one way and and
uh but what i learned from these studies is that
we have a really diverse records so for the 70k
model yes i weighted everything equally for the
100k i think we did not weight them equally um
probably uh checking regional consistency again
and and getting some number that will be added to
the random end of the systematic uh and i think
there are some studies maybe not on this time
scales but on the shorter holes in time scales
that uh that incorporate all of these errors
into one error and this is how they are rated
thank you very much um i'll draw how to draw
the uh seminar to close we can save any last
questions for for um the uh the catch up
at the end end of it all so i just want to
um invite everybody to give uh sanyo another
virtual round of applause for uh another great
talk on our my seminar series so thank you very
much uh for coming and presenting to us today
and now before uh everybody um leaves
just a quick a couple of uh reminders
for um our seminar series we have another
uh seminar series in a couple of weeks um
by from gwen williams from edinburgh uh and
then after uh egu we will switch to a an eu
uh eastern hemisphere time slot so there will be
a change uh in the time of our magnet seminars um
and we'll run that slot from about june to august
or so and there'll be more announcements about
speakers that we have lined up for for that
session and as always we're looking for more
uh people to um to present to the seminars
and in particular we always encourage
uh early career speakers to put themselves forward
for presenting a seminar and for anybody who has
missed our seminars in the past um all of
our recordings are on our youtube channel
so please um uh go on to there subscribe for the
announcements and catch up with all the seminar
series going all the way back to our very first uh
seminars back in in 2020 but uh once again thank
you everybody for uh joining magnets this week
and we'll see you in a couple of weeks time cheers